oh
[Music]
good evening good day everybody welcome
to episode 60 of the ask a budget show
it's good to see you all let me see who
all is there with us today let us see
who are there
i can see
i can see nathan monish pranav harsh
sandeep sleep
bharat samaat gautam aryan rishi
ayush
gokul
and lots of other people
great to see you all great to see you
all
so what shall we discuss today
what questions do you all have let's
take
let's take some questions
let's see what all you've been asking
okay let's begin with this question it's
by gayatri
gayatri says
you said in one session india didn't get
freedom in 1947 it was a transfer of
power
so what do we need to do to get freedom
what will freedom look like will we ever
get there i think we'll certainly get
there what do we need to get freedom we
need to decolonize completely we haven't
even begun the process of decolonization
i mean if you go to the judiciary in
india they will insist that you speak in
english if you speak in a local language
they'll throw you out
there is
colonization we are still colonized
our constitution is a colonial
constitution
right it is it is a western constitution
it doesn't it is not based in indian
values in in indian culture it is based
in western values and western morality
our laws are still most of them are
still british laws i mean what sort of
joke is this we are still a colonized
nation freedom is decolonization we need
our institutions our constitution our
laws to be indian in nature based on
indian values indian principles
indian culture
and our governance system has to be
indian in nature not this fake democracy
that is only democracy in name
in a real democracy all the institutions
are accountable to the people
in every democracy in the world
in the west etc the judiciary is
accountable to the people it is
appointed by the people it can be
dismissed by the people a judge can be
dismissed for non-performance
can that happen in india
so this is called colonization we are
completely colonized and most of us
don't even realize it
our our laws are so so regressive
so incredibly hindu phobic and so on so
that's why we are not
really free we will be free only when we
get rid of the colonial baggage it's the
process hasn't even started because it
suits the politicians to keep india this
way
because that way they are able to rule
us instead of service
right
so that that's what freedom will look
like when we change all this it it can
happen hopefully it will happen
when will we ever get there i don't know
i would like to see it happen tomorrow
but it's not going to happen tomorrow
maybe in the next 20 30 years perhaps
i would like to see it in our lifetimes
yeah
so that's what i that's what i meant by
we did not get freedom in 1947 we still
don't have
freedom okay what else do we have
let's take another question
[Laughter]
from which university did you study does
it matter from where i studied have i
learned anything from any university i
went to school college university did i
ever learn anything from that i mean
whatever knowledge i have which is why
you come and see these sessions do you
think i acquired that knowledge in
school college university
i acquired none of that in school
college university educ the education
system is a complete and total waste of
time the only reason why we have to go
through the education system
is to acquire a degree because you can
you cannot get a job unless you have a
degree you you have no status in society
unless you have a degree
so education is all for degrees and
status that's all it is but it's all
pointless it's worthless it doesn't
contribute anything to society
i i have not learned anything of value
unfortunately from school college or
university i cannot think of a single
class i attended a single lecture that i
attended in which i learned something
that i did not already know
i have learned everything through
self-study
i don't remember a single teacher who
impressed me
that that's just the way it is i mean
think back to your childhood to when you
attended school college whatever
did you really learn anything there you
had to learn everything on your own
through homework and through going home
and
studying the textbooks on your own or
going to tuition classes or whatever
just
randomly mugging up stuff
right
so that's how it is so it doesn't matter
in india in every in any other country
also i mean today everyone knows this
cam that is the ivy league education
system in the united states it's a scam
and that's how it is so the real
knowledge that you can acquire is is
something you do through self-study i
don't have any
guru
i have learned nobody has ever taught me
anything
that is the sad truth i have learned
everything on my own so it doesn't
matter which university i went to
it's immaterial it's pointless the
knowledge that i whatever little
knowledge i have i have acquired it on
my own because of my curiosity
and because i invested
i don't know how many hours reading
various books and various other sources
of knowledge so
that's what it is
all right
let's see some more questions
so basedgamer says india's average iq is
given as 82. is it true or some
euro-centric data
i
see you know i'm not sure how accurate
iq is in actually
measuring someone's real intelligence
uh the the the guy what's his name
nassim nicholas taleb calls iq a pseudo
scientific swindle
right that's that's point number one so
iq may not accurately reflect how
intelligent a person may be
right but it does
show some cognitive abilities and it's
and things like that
uh people who achieve who are who are
great achievers
typically tend to have higher iqs so
there could be some relation but it may
not be entirely accurate now india's
average iq who has decided that india's
average iq is 82
on on the basis of how much data
and is that data actually representative
of the of the nation as a whole 1.3
billion people i don't think india's
average iq would be 82 i think indians
are the most intelligent people in the
world
more intelligent than the chinese more
intelligent than the jews more
intelligent than the europeans americans
i think indians are the most intelligent
people in the world
so i if the whoever is decided or or
calculated india's average iq is 82 they
need to have their own iq examined again
i'd say
right
armed forces lover says the role of
china in the manipur attack and at the
same time the presence of chinese army
and pok any relation between them so
that pok is in the north west of india
manipur is in the extreme east of india
so there is no relationship between the
presence of the chinese
soldiers in pok
and what happened in manipur
that's thousands of kilometers
apart
but i would say that the chinese
certainly have a role in whatever
insurgency
has uh occurred in the north and in the
in the eastern we call it the northeast
it's actually the far east of india so
whatever has happened in the past in the
past
since the 1950s 60s etc whatever
insurgencies
have uh erupted in the northeast
uh they they these uh movements emerged
for a certain reason that had nothing to
do with china
but the chinese certainly took advantage
of that and and fanned the flames they
have supported various terrorist
organizations
uh in manipur in nagala and nagaland
it's still you know very much active
there is a lot of separate is a
separatist sentiment in nagaland which
is mainly fanned by two
uh forces one is the chinese
and the second is the west through the
through the catholic church
so that is certainly there yes
now what is the role of china and the
manipura tech uh
i'm not sure which terrorist
organization is responsible for this
attack
manipur has been a hotbed of of
insurgency and terrorism since the 1960s
and 70s it all started for a certain
reason
and later these terrorist outfits just
began became
essentially
gangs of extortionists
and the politicians were at a certain
point in time very deeply involved in
that
so i'm not sure which terrorist
organization has uh claimed
responsibility or if any of them has
claimed responsibility
uh there you know manipur actually half
of manipur is more than half of manipur
i think 80 of manipur is currently uh
the the people see it's like this
manipur is about 40 45 hindu
the rest is all christians converted
converted tribals
the hindus are confined to just one
place in manipur the manipur valley the
infall valley
let's take a look at the map you know
that that will make things easier to
understand
uh okay let me share my screen
okay let's go to maps
maps
let's go to manipur
so
we have manipur here
so this is the state of manipur
and now we have this this
okay i'm not sure if you're able to see
this
let me stop it and let me share it again
okay this is the state of manipur
if you can see here this is manipur and
this is the imphal valley region this is
the only place where you have manipura
hindus the methane is
and all other parts of manipur are
are in the possession
the people who live there are tribals
who are converted to christianity
and in manipur also you have this uh
this weird law there like we had in
kashmir
which did not allow
which essentially
doesn't allow hindus to buy land outside
the impal valley
hindus can only live in the infall
valley and they are not allowed by law
to buy land anywhere else
so the entirety of manipur 80 90 of it
has been is now occupied by people who
owe allegiance to nagaland
they call themselves nagas right so a
significant portion of the uh
well
terrorism so to say
in manipur is actually done by uh
various naga outfits and many of them
let me share this again
and many of these naga outfits actually
uh operate from across the border in
burma this region if you can see my
mouse pointer is burma myanmar
and this region is home to the same
tribal groups that are present in
manipur
so many of these activities happen from
across the border
if you remember a few years ago we had
to do a surgical strike in burmese
territory on the on one of the naga
terrorist outfits the kaplan group i
think it was
and the chinese have been supporting
these groups if you look here
it's just a few couple of hundred
kilometers and then you have the yunnan
province of china over here
so they essentially ferry arms
ammunition supplies across burma
into manipura nagaland
and that's how these terrorist outfits
are supplied by the chinese so i think
it's quite
it's quite possible
that the chinese have a hand in this one
of their spokes people the the
spokesperson
the editor of the uh global times he
actually tweeted about this that we can
use
we can support uh separatists and
terrorists in india's northeast as one
of the ways to retaliate against india
so they it's part of their official
policy so it's quite possible that the
chinese have a hand in this and if there
is a case they need to be totalizing
this cannot be allowed to go on
so right so that's the answer sir
okay let's take some other question
this is by lata ramesh
please give your opinion about kangana's
statement about independence given in
1947 is a biksha or or it's it's a
donation
do you agree with her or do you condem
condemn her statement
i do not condemn her statement she is
right
like i said earlier we did not get any
real independence it was given to us on
the terms
of the british we did not get the kind
of independence we wanted we actually
got dominion status in 1947 then
according to historians dominion status
was revoked in 1950 and we became a
fully independent republic
i will
you know there are many people who still
dispute that claim that we may still be
under dominion status and the papers and
all the documents have not been ever
made
public so independence is never given it
is taken let me let me uh show
what mustafa kemal ataturk had to say
about this
all right
so okay well let me share my screen here
we are
what did mustafa kemal ataturk have to
say about sovereignty so mustafa kamal
ataturk was the
founder of turkey
he liberated turkey in the turkish war
of independence in the 1920s early 1920s
this is what he had to say about
sovereignty sovereignty and the right to
rule cannot be conferred on anyone no
matter who as a result of an academic
discussion
sovereignty is acquired by force and
power and violence
sovereignty is not given it is taken
and this guy fought
he fought for turkey's independence he
got turkey
he made turkey an independent nation
on his own terms not on the terms of the
western powers the western the western
nations had divided turkey into a number
of pieces
and they supported the ottoman caliph
abdul hamid the second i think his name
was
and it was the kind of thing we have in
india today it was a rule based on
western values
it was independence
quasi-independence for turkey based on
what the west prescribed for turkey on
on the on the terms of the west of the
western nations the nations that were
where that won
the the first world war
so it was a humiliation for turkey and
that was not in accordance to
what the turkish people wanted so
mustafa kabal ataturk fought the war of
independence he defeated all the all of
these
occupation powers and he acquired
independence for turkey on his own terms
so that's why turkey is able to pursue
an independent geopolitical policy and
you may agree with it or not even i may
not agree with it but at least they are
genuinely independent
right
so we are not genuinely independent we
are still
laboring under the weight of colonialism
so so kangana ranath is completely right
independence it was not independence we
are still colonized if you're colonized
you're not independent and whatever
so-called independence we got was
dominion status it was a transfer of
power from one set of crooks to another
set of crooks appointed by the first set
of crooks
right
so so she's right i agree with her
all right let's uh
take some more questions
ahman asks does india have any benefit
of s 400 what aman is saying is
what is the benefit of acquiring the s
system for india i mean we would not try
to acquire something that expensive
and something you have to wait for for
so long if it were not of some
significant use for us so what is the
s-400 system it's a missile defense
system
uh it has a range maximum range of 400
kilometers so you can take out you can
destroy incoming missiles or aircraft
etc
at a range of 400 kilometers or less
typically you would do it within a range
of 100 kilometers so this is a
russian-made system they had the s-200
earlier then the s-300
and now we have the s-400 they have
already developed the s 500 which is an
even more advanced system
and that has not been exported anywhere
else thus far so the russians are
exporting it to us we they have begun
the first deliveries iron dr we have
received the first shipments of the s400
and they will be installed on the
northern border with
against china the chinese also have the
system so the russians uh sold the
system to the chinese
but then they sold it to india as well
which tells you that they are not
as friendly with china as people would
make it look like
so india is acquiring this this is the
best system of its class in the world it
is better than the us
aegis class system
uh what is the system called i think
it's the aegis system it's it's the
system that's installed on the aegis
class destroyers
that form the defense
entourage of the
aircraft carrier strike forces in the
u.s navy and so on
so uh the s-400 is far better than that
system it is better than the iron dome
system of israel which is something
that's localized in a small region and
so on so forth so it's the best system
of its class in the world
and it is going to give india the
ability to wipe out any target any any
any potential chinese incursions through
air via
with fighter aircraft or through cruise
missiles or even possibly ballistic
missiles it's primarily
an anti-aircraft system
so it can take out lots of aircraft at
the same time it can track multiple
aircraft and take them out it has
multiple layers multiple layers of
missile defenses and so on so it's a
very good system
it is certainly worth buying the system
the turks have acquired it the chinese
have acquired it and now we are on in
the process of getting the deliveries
so it is really good it's possibly a
game changer for india because you see
new delhi
is just a few hundred kilometers away
from the from the tibet border
and the chinese
would possibly want to do a decapitation
strike if we if we go to war with them
someday if they initiate a war with us
so it's certainly good to have the
system
and yeah so it is certainly beneficial
for india
this is by anish abraham
huge fan from johannesburg so nice to
have uh
have you here from johannesburg nice to
meet you
uh please tell us more about the
tokarians are they the ancestors of the
tari mummies the huns etc good question
so who were the tokkarians
okay let me go back to the map
map map map
oh yeah i need to share the map
just a minute let me share it
so the tokarians are an ancient uh
population group they used to live
in this region here
you see this here is india as you know
if you go north of kashmir
then you reach
this part of
this geographical region which is
currently part of china's xinjiang
province
this is the tarim river basin
so uh this is where these people used to
live the tokarian people you find these
mummies very well preserved mummies the
mummies are very well preserved
and these are very very old mummies
several thousand years old like
typically three four thousand year old
mummies they are very well preserved
because of the extreme
dryness of this region
this was once a fertile region the
tharium river basin
i think this is the hotan river but
there is a tarim river also somewhere
here
so this is the tharium river basin and
that's where these dokarin mummies are
found and they have also found uh
pieces of ancient text etc
so in india in the ancient days these
people were called the tushar people and
the tokarian name comes essentially from
the tushar from the from the word we had
for them the tosharas
so who are these people so if you look
at the mummies if you look at the
mummies of these people they look more
like europeans than indians they are
typically many of them are many of the
males are about six feet tall or even
taller than that
many of them have red hair or blonde
hair
and so so that's that's how they look
but if you examine their genetics those
are indian genetics r1a1a which is the
indian
haplogroup it originated in india about
between 18 and 26 thousand years before
today
so it these people had indian origin
petroleum genetics yes
but they looked more european than
indian like than present day indian
so red hair blonde hair all that tall
fair skin etc because we have very well
preserved mummies and their language is
called the karin language the tushar
language so let's see what that language
looks looked like let me see
so let us look at what their language
look like
so this is the it's an extinct language
it's about four thousand three and a
half thousand four thousand years old
and this is the script the independent
vowels and all that now if you look at
the consonants of this language it goes
like this
this sounds exactly like sanskrit or
hindi or any indian language
right
so that is how the sister the
the classification of the language was
uh
linguists classified the tokarian
language as part of the centum group of
languages of indo-european languages
for instance uh persian sanskrit hindi
the indian languages etc these are
classified as shatam languages satam
and greek and latin etcetera are
classified as centum languages so
linguists have classified the tokarian
language as a centum language not as a
shattam language and yet you can see the
significant similarity between this
language and
the way the indian languages are
classified and the consonants and all
that even the script actually looks
somewhat like
many indian scripts
so that's how it is
so this is one of the uh
ethnic groups
that is attested in ancient indian texts
like the ramayana the mahabharata etc i
think the the toshara people
participated in the mahabharata war
and so on
so it is quite likely that this is an
ethnic group that at some point in the
distant past traveled out of india we
know of many migrations that are tested
in ancient indian texts migrations out
of india
northwards out of india westwards out of
india this is most likely one of those
ancient groups that migrated out of
india many other groups are known the
amne are the skits etc etc etc the
entirety of europe was populated by
indian origin people who migrated long
ago out of india
and then these tusharas
they seem to be the ancestors of the
kushans
so we know that the kushans
invaded
and conquered parts of northern india
about
2100 or so years ago and they
established a very powerful dynasty a
very very
great dynasty kush uh kanishka kushan
was one of was the greatest emperor was
our greatest emperor one of our greatest
emperors
and he was in no me by no means a
foreigner he did more to promote and
strengthen indian culture than any
almost any other emperor that i can
think of since since his time
and as you can see they had indian
genetics and they spoke in indic
kind of language
so yes the tokarians are essentially the
tarim mummies
and they are most likely the ancestors
of the kushans i don't think they have
anything to do with the huns
the huns are a different ethnic group
the old hounds were called the sure new
by the chinese
and uh
the the
the kushans what were they called by the
chinese they were called the uhc or
something so it's a different ethnic
group right
so i don't th
they are not related to the huns but
they are certainly related to the
kushans so that's what i can tell you in
brief about the takarians and the
thorium mummies of fascinating chapter
of history and very good question
mark max says very big fan thank you
keep keep up the good work thank you
thank you very much joshua thank you
thank you very much
all right let's take some more questions
a sonali i have answered many times so
you can check out my older
my own some of my old video clips
or somebody says why have indo-russia
relations deteriorated over the years
see the world changes
geopolitical equations change
we there is no such thing as friendship
in geopolitics it's all about
convergence of interests so in the
during the cold war era in the 20th
century india was a satellite state of
the russians
it is because of the policies of the
great shri jawaharlal nehru right
he was a lover of socialism he was
a lover of
whatever else you know
fabian socialism so he chose to adopt
the soviet socialist model
and he did not even do that properly so
it led to the horrific nairobian rate of
rate of growth that stifled india's
development in the in the
during most of the 20th century
but india was a geopolitically a good
ally to have for the soviet union and
that's why india and russia had very
strong relations during that time
it's because india was very useful to
the ussr
as something
as a counterweight to american influence
in asia
and that's why we had very good
relations and they used to supply
various weapons and things like that to
india the mig-21 and various other
things
some submarines etc
now after the collapse of the ussr
the
and the breakout breakaway of of the
various central asian republics et
cetera russia's priorities changed it
first became
a capitalist economy during boris yes in
time which was a horrific mismanagement
of the country the country went deep
into poverty then vladimir putin took
over and he has strengthened russia
again
now the world has changed it is no
longer a unipolar world with one single
superpower now we have the chinese
threat
the chinese are a threat to india they
are threatened to russia also but the us
is so anti-russia that the russians have
kind of
created a quasi alliance with the
chinese because
because their interests currently align
now india is drifting towards the us as
something that will help it in its uh
to to
counter balance china and that's why
our
interests don't align as strongly with
the russians as they used to earlier
but we do have a common enemy in china
and that's why we still have reasonably
good relations and there is a great deal
of warmth between the two between the
two nations between the peoples of the
two nations etc and between the
leadership leadership also
i think mr modi and mr putin have a very
good equation you know personal equation
i think mr putin is supposed to visit
india in the near future so we'll see
how that goes that will be interesting
so i think they haven't really
deteriorated the relations aren't bad in
any way
but they are no longer as strong as they
used to be because of these reasons
that currently the russians are involved
in afghanistan because they want to
they want to maintain a certain presence
in central asia which they regard as
their traditional sphere of influence
they don't don't want the chinese to
gain too much influence in this region
and the russians are also
in some way
they are associated associating in in a
variety of ways
with the pakistanis also which they
never did in the past
so they are doing whatever serves their
interests best and we have to do
whatever serves our interests best
that's how the game of geopolitics is
played there is no friendship
and and such like right there are no
friendships and enmities
you have
interests national interest that's
that's the main driver of everything you
do so that's the status of
india in russia and the relations
between these two
nations
somia says what is the origin of the
people of pakistan balochs punjabis
pakhtuns sindhis i mean
do i have to answer this
the origin of the people of pakistan is
india
pakistan is indian territory
i'm really surprised to see this
question
if pakistani goes abroad do they look
like a separate ethnicity from indians
no
pakistanis afghans pashtuns punjabis
balochis
kashmiris
and so on and so forth these are all
indians
it's the indian ethnicities the indian
genetics indian languages
but it's a different religion and
culture which is why it's a separate
country
so that's the answer
okay let's take some more questions
um
says recently a woman was found
suffering from breathlessness in canada
the reports are saying this is the first
case of climate change in the world how
serious is the problem of climate change
she was suffering this was a person who
was suffering from asthma and various in
diabetes and some other conditions and
the doctor decided to diagnose her with
climate change climate change is not a
medical condition
this is just to gain publicity or or the
spotlight in the media
climate change is not a medical
condition
right
so it is just a publicity stunt that
this doctor did but how serious is the
problem of climate change it exists it
is there you cannot deny the fact that
climate climate change is the real thing
cli the see the the earth's climate has
been
changing ever since the earth was formed
climate change is a
natural process but in the last 300 400
years it is certainly it certainly has
a
component which is because of human
activity as well so since the industrial
revolution the europeans
burned so much coal and and oil and all
that
to to kick start their economy and make
them prosperous that it has
released an enormous amount of carbon
dioxide in the atmosphere
i would say the majority of all the
carbon dioxide in the atmosphere which
has
been released since
in the past 3 400 years the majority of
it is because of the western nations
and today they are trying to blame india
and china for it
which is nonsense but yes there is
certainly uh
human activity is certainly a
significant cause of climate change
today
especially all the carbon that has been
released into the atmosphere all the
deforestation that is happening
and so on and so forth it is a serious
problem
so that's what i can say about this yes
says what is the contribution of
literature particularly fiction in the
development of a society literature is
part of culture isn't it fiction is part
of culture
of there are various kinds of literature
there is literary fiction there is a
pulp fiction popular fiction there is
poetry there is there's a lot
so it is certainly a very significant
component of a society's culture
and the kind of literature
and fiction that is popular in a society
is an excellent barometer
it's a it's an excellent indicator
of the attitudes and mindset of the
society
so if you look at in not just literature
and fiction the kind of games you play
the kind of content you consume online
uh
the games i mean if you look at let's
let's take american society for instance
uh
there's this deep-rooted gaming culture
today every kid plays games right
xbox or playstation or online games or
minecraft or roblox or whatever if you
look at the nature of these games what
do you see it's all about shooting and
killing
that's the kind of culture that is
prevalent in in american society that's
the kind of mindset and attitudes
that you have there and the result of
that is that every other week there is a
school shooting or a mall shooting or
something or a mass shooting somewhere
so it is an excellent barometer of the
kind of attitudes and mindset that a
society has
and again if you look at literature and
fiction it also reflects the same
for instance look at india
there is almost no
literature or fiction being produced in
india in indian languages
so that tells you that indians are
losing touch with their roots right
and whatever is being uh published in
english it's unfortunately very mediocre
in my opinion in my personal opinion i
have certain standards they may differ
from your standards or other people's
standards i am saying it from my
perspective right from my perspective
the kind of literature we have in this
country is ridiculously mediocre
um so it reflects the kind of uh
society that that we have today
unfortunately indians are not a mediocre
people
indian society is not mediocre it's a
great great culture the oldest
civilization the greatest civilization
but we are passing through a phase of
mediocrity which is
the result of all the social engineering
through the education system the media
and all that
right i i get the feeling that inside
the head of every indian there is a
bollywood song going on at every at any
given point in time
so that's the kind of brainwashing and
mindset we have in this country today
there is no science fiction being
written in india why is that
because there is no understanding of
science there is no understanding of
what future one would like to envisage
there is no science fiction being
produced in india
that is so disappointing so yes you know
the literature and fiction is an
excellent barometer
of the state of society at any given
point in time very interesting question
very good observation
right right
okay this is by shyam do you think that
india has plans to take back pok in the
near future as the s 400 is deployed on
the pakistan border
i don't know where the s400 has been
deployed i don't think it's a good idea
for the government to announce that it's
been deployed here or there
i would expect that it will be deployed
on the tibet border
pakistan is not such a big threat we can
deal with pakistan in
in other ways
uh it is mainly to counter the chinese
threat that we have purchased the s400
that's that's my assessment
and i don't think the government has
made any any announcements of where
the system is or will be deployed
so that's point number one now does
india have plans to get pok back
of course it does we will get poke back
when it will happen i am not privy to
those plans so i can't say
but i would say in the next 5-10 years
it will happen
maximum 10 years
when the time is right and we will make
the conditions right before we can
before we go ahead with whatever needs
to be done right
so i think it will happen within the
next five to ten years but as for uh as
far as the s 400 system goes i
personally believe it will be deployed
it will be more useful on the tibet
border
all right
uh tenjin tamang says what will be the
breakthrough discovery in the 21st
century in science
so science has lots of different uh
domains different spheres when it comes
to technology you have artificial
intelligence you have a drone technology
that has revolutionized everything you
may have flying cars and all but that is
not really something that will uh that
will be accessible to everybody it's
going to be something like a luxury
thing but artificial intelligence
machine learning
these algorithms that permeate the
entire entire human social sphere today
that is one of the big things that has
changed the world in the last 10 20
years
but what will be the breakthrough
discovery let's say in physics i would
say i would like to
um
we need to understand the force of
gravity better we don't understand
gravity we still are stuck in the 20
early 20th century the
general theory of theory of relativity
was uh
discovered and published in 1915 ever
since then we have
achieved
no further understanding of the force of
gravity
and that is what is impeding of our
understanding of the universe today
because we don't know what dark matter
is what dark energy is we think the
black holes of singularity is therein
but actually there is a mathematical
blowing blowing up of the einstein field
equations so what i would like to see
hopefully is uh the discovery or the
understanding of the quantum nature of
gravity if you can achieve that
breakthrough it will completely
transform and revolutionize our
understanding of the universe and the
laws that
govern it
so that would be a breakthrough
discovery in theoretical physics in pure
in pure physics
in technological discoveries these
occur
in an incremental fashion
for instance artificial intelligence is
not something that suddenly was thrown
upon us it's being and it's been under
development since the 1960s you know but
only now with the kind of computing
power that we have
have we been able to implement it at the
scale that we see it
today
so in pure physics i would like to see
the the
discovery of the and of of the quantum
nature of gravity
uh so that would be for me
personally the breakthrough discovery in
21st century
the 21st century was supposed to be the
century of gravitation thus far it has
not been hopefully it will happen
deepan bhattacharya says why do most
indian parents discover discourage their
child from doing research it's because
of the
climate of scarcity in india you don't
have enough jobs
to uh
for everybody
right
i mean everybody wants a high paying job
everybody needs a high paying job to to
live a decent middle-class life
lifestyle
anything below middle class is poverty
right nobody wants their children to
suffer in poverty
and that's why
parents parents are afraid for the
children's futures right
that's why they want the children to do
well in school and college and
university whatever get the degree with
high marks and high high
percentages and all that
and then get a nice safe job in some
industry in the government sector or
private sector or whatever and then have
kids and
all that
that is the safe approach
and because there are so few jobs there
are so few seats in college and
university there are so few jobs
available there is such a scarcity of
jobs
that's why parents want children to
focus only on academics on mugging up
everything getting the highest marks
getting the degrees
so that they can get one of those few
precious jobs
if children start doing research because
they have the intelligence and the
aptitude for that
where are the research jobs in this
country
how many research institutions do we
have
either in biology in biochemistry
physics science astronomy
computing
technology do we have any research
institutes
do we have private companies that that
encourage research for instance in the
us lots of private companies do their
research in-house
so there is a great demand for talented
researchers in technology in physics in
mathematics in the finance sector and so
on in india there is no such thing
because the government has not
created
the right kind of environment
for entrepreneurship and startups today
things are changing okay so let's not
say nothing is happening
but it's we are not there yet
we have not yet reached the kind of uh
we have not yet constructed or created
the kind of environment you have for
instance in silicon valley
where where good ideas great ideas get
funding you don't need to
beg people for funding you will get
funds if you have a good idea and your
your project will take off
so indians
like i said they are they are the people
who are essentially
the core of silicon valley they are the
ones driving all the research and all
the progress all the technology in the
us
so
it tells you how intelligent and how
creative and how brilliant indians are
and we have 1.3 billion billion billion
indians in india
so imagine if you unleash the true
potential of of indians in india what
they will be able to achieve
so that's why we need to create this
environment and once that happens once
there will be opportunities for research
when they'll once there'll be a great
demand for intelligent
talented brilliant researchers then
indian parents will realize that it is
fine
to do research they will then encourage
the children to do research
because then the opportunities will be
available so it is something you we have
to understand
the majority of parents want their
children to do well in life right
so
that is why they discourage the children
from doing research because they see the
world from a different perspective they
have seen
they have experienced the world more
in in
at greater depths than the children have
and so it
unfortunately it does make sense right
that's how it is
all right
okay let's take some more questions
malika says
once said that 95 of existing sanskrit
manuscripts are not translated
do you think that these texts may
contain critical knowledge about math
and sciences which is still unexplored
so i agree with the statement that more
than 95 of
the texts that are available are not
translated they have not been catalogued
they have not been digitized they are
crumbling and turning into dust
and that is the crying shame in this
country that we simply don't care about
our heritage
and it is the government's
responsibility to to do this the asi and
other organizations who simply don't
care
it's a crying shame i think there could
be a lot of valuable
knowledge
that could open up uh
new paradigms for us right
it could give us a much richer
understanding of our past of what our
ancestors lifestyle was like what
achievements they did what uh
knowledge they discovered about
mathematics about the sciences certainly
it is certainly very possible
there could be certain mathematical
discoveries that we are not aware of
possibly
so yes i agree
that those texts may contain very
interesting uh
facts about our ancient history that we
have lost and and and the discoveries in
mathematics and the sciences that we are
not aware of
and that is why i have been saying for a
very long time we need to
preserve those manuscripts we need to
digitize all of them that's the first
step
and then translate them into various
other indian languages english also for
if the world wants to
uh
partake in the knowledge
yeah so that that should happen there
should be a
project for doing that
and unfortunately it's not happening
right now what is the ministry of
culture doing they have the funds
they have the funds every state
government has the funds to do this but
they won't do it
i was once on a tv
debate
about uh
about some excavation or something in in
the state of orissa
and there was
a gentleman from the orissa government
on on the tv on the tv discussion
and they were talking about the fact
that the monsoon is coming that's why we
are gonna have to stop the
archaeological work for a few months and
so on
so i asked these people ask the
gentleman that you have the funds and
everything
why don't you create a world-class
museum one only one museum in orissa
where you can keep all these priceless
artifacts so that the people of orissa
kalinga can see what their heritage is
like
and this gentleman was unable to answer
me because he agreed we have the funds
but it looks like there is no political
will and i'm not trying to single out
the state of orissa this applies to
every state in india
and the entire indian governance system
they simply don't care they have the
funds to do everything they want
they have the funds to create one
world-class museum in every indian state
but there is no political will for that
you know and we have the funds to
digitize and preserve all the
manuscripts easily
but there is no will to do that it is
not
a priority which is so disappointing
okay
okay what about this question skd says
is a war expected between india and
china in the near future
it feels like a war is coming china
entering pok and asking their citizens
to stock on food and so on it does
appear like a war is coming i'm not sure
where the war will be
the chinese are more concerned about
taiwan
they want to uh
integrate taiwan they want to uh conquer
and annex taiwan
and make it part of china because
the island of taiwan is ruled by a
different system under a different
system it is a democratic
separate nation the chinese say it's not
a separate nation it's part of china
well unfortunately that's not the
reality
so they want to conquer china but what
about india and china because see the
chinese have
massed a significant number of troops
on the tibetan border with india and
india has
responded in kind india has also massed
up for force
forces
and other things infrastructure
equipment on the on the tibet border
to counter the chinese buildup over
there
so yeah it is possible that you may have
a chinese misadventure they may try to
do another short sharp war
like in 1962
if they try it they are welcome to try
but then they should be ready for what
what comes next
so it is possible
that a war may be initiated by the
chinese
with india in the near future
and it is also possible they may try to
initiate um
they may try to attempt an invasion of
taiwan if they are stupid enough to do
that
because uh typically the chinese are
very risk averse they don't do something
unless they uh they feel that they are
certain to win
but right now the chinese economy is
slowing down significantly
uh there are all these bankruptcies of
big companies like evergrand etc so it
may push the chinese leadership into a
corner and make them desperate
to grab whatever they can while they
still have the chance
before the economy goes down further
so yeah that makes people desperate and
that's where you kind
kind of try and stretch
and grasp whatever you can so that may
cause china china to indulge in a
misadventure maybe with india or maybe
with taiwan we are i think quite
prepared for it
and yeah so it is a possibility
let's see maybe in the next few months
maybe the next year or two it may happen
i hope it doesn't happen but if it
happens we will teach them a lesson
says what is the contribution of
amortisan in india's economy his
contribution is zero
okay let's
okay what about this question ashish
buddha says why does no one talk about
the massacre of native americans
it's a very inconvenient thing to talk
about
because it will expose the fact that the
continent of north america and south
america
actually belongs to the natives
not to the european origin people
the continent was stolen from the native
americans
and uh there was this horrific genocide
that took place over there over
a couple of centuries
i would say at least a hundred million
native americans were massacred in north
america
at the hands of the european
uh invaders
the british the french etc
and their land was stolen from them
and that is the present-day nations of
canada and the united states
and even today they are essentially
second-class citizens the natives in
these two countries they live
in reservations
where there is no infrastructure there
isn't there are no facilities nothing
and there is a great deal of racism
against them
so certain kinds of lives don't matter
in america
there is the truth about
about america
you know so it's very inconvenient to
talk about native americans and what
they had to undergo
so that's why no one talks about it
dev sharma says should we really support
taiwan because at the end of the day
they also claim arunachal pradesh and
tibet as well so what would be the
difference if taiwan is in power there
would be no difference
uh the government of taiwan also
considers tibet in arunachal pradesh to
be part of china so there is no real
difference
you see so we have to indians
they don't see the big picture
unfortunately because we are not taught
this we don't have access to this
information and indians are very
they they they feel that we should be
big fans of taiwan and big fans of
various certain other countries
and they don't see whether the the
the same kind of feeling is reciprocated
or not
if taiwan was really a friend like
indians like to say a friend of india
then would they ever claim tibet to be
part of china and arunachal pradesh to
be part of china they would not
they would respect
the feelings of the people of tibet
and india's perceptions of its
boundaries
they don't respect it
so you know what
that's that's the reason why
the indian government at least is not
that strong in supporting
taiwan people ask me why doesn't india
support taiwan why didn't india come out
in support of taiwan well that's one
reason why
the taiwan is at the same attitude as
the chinese communist party when it
comes to the india china boundaries and
the dispute which the which well it's
it's something that's left over from
history it is something that we should
have solved in the 1940s and 50s but we
did not
so that's the reality they also claim
the same thing
isn't it interesting
uh mr right trooper says why was the
indian subcontinent always invaded from
the west but not the east
for instance bengal faced invasions from
the west despite it is situated despite
being situated on the very east of the
region
well yeah it's an interesting question
maybe because there was no significant
uh empire to the east
and there was no abrahamic religion that
one that emerged in the east right
so maybe it's just an accident of
history we did have migrations into
india from the east for instance the
thai people
they migrated into present-day assam
they are called the home people they are
the ancestors of the home people
so if you look at the culture of assam
it is a beautiful syncretic culture
which has elements of the thai culture
and the old thai religion or our
belief system
and it is now mixed with indian
indian culture
indian genetics and all that so it's a
very interesting mixture
so you had a migration of this
of this ethnic group into assam
but yes typically you will you have to
if you look at the big picture there has
been no actual invasion of india from
the east it's always been from the west
and the invasions have also happened
from from the north for instance you had
the
uh this kitchen and hunnic invasions and
also the kushan invasions
now the kushan invasion the hunik
invasion the skins invasion were not
in any way as destructive as the
turkic invasions because the huns who
tried to invade india they eventually
succeeded to some extent they peacefully
and harmoniously
assimilated into the indian indian
population they did not try to impose a
foreign language foreign culture on
india they adopted indian culture and
religion and traditions
the huns the same goes for the kittens
who essentially were indian origin
people if you go back a few thousand
years before that and same goes for the
kushans descendants of the takarians the
shara people
so these were invasions that did not
really
uh
harm india's culture and demographics in
any way the turkic invasions and the
subsequent european invasions are what
really harmed india so if you look at
the bigger picture it's always been
waves of migrations out of india a few
small scale invasions into india
but what's changed is what happened in
the past 1000 or so years after the
emergence
of the abrahamic religions to the west
okay let's take some more questions
my views on bibi lal receiving the padma
bhushan
can you briefly explain some of his
interesting theories and overall career
it's a great thing that he got this
award while he is still alive
he could most likely most probably be
the world's greatest living
archaeologist
in the west they called dr zahi hawas
the egyptian egyptiologist
to be the world's greatest archaeologist
i disagree i think dr professor bibi lal
is the greatest archaeologist in the
world he was the head of the asi and he
he actually did some good work
as the head of the asi
and his career as an archaeologist uh
spans spans more than 50 years more than
five decades he published lots of
articles lots of books about indian
archaeology
and he disagreed with the rn invasion
theory he demonstrated that this theory
is false
but his uh
his voluminous
body of work was never incorporated into
india into india's history textbooks
they marginalized him they sidelined him
the indian historians
so it is great that he has got this
recognition i'm really happy for him
uh his theories overall career so i
that's what it is it's like 50 years he
has published some very interesting
books i have a couple of his books
somewhere here the rig vedic people is
one book that i can refer refer
recommend to you the right vedic people
by dr b bilal
it's about the archaeological findings
in the
saraswatis in the region
it shows that these people
there is this continuity of culture and
traditions
from the
harappan times to the present day in
india which means it shows that the this
culture etc did not come from central
asia or eastern europe or whatever
without the so-called aryans it's always
been part of india and so on so that's a
little bit about him
so you can uh i would highly recommend
that you acquire a couple of his books
such as the rigvedic people which will
give you a better understanding of
his work
oh yeah i think i answered this question
his contribution to india's economy is
zero is he a communist he's a marxist
yeah
yes
the best book to learn sanskrit is what
chinmay solanki asks there's a book in
hindi called sanskrit swayam
very good book
if you study that book you'll be able to
start speaking
in sanskrit within half an hour
and within three months you will have a
reasonable mastery conversational
mastery of the language you won't become
a real master of the language but you
will be able to actually have
conversations and understand the
language
reasonably well just three months
so it's called sanskrit swayam shikshak
it's a hindi language book it's not in
english
but it's the best book i have ever found
for learning sanskrit
okay let's
see what else
we have
oops
hang in there
okay sid says i read an article in india
facts it claims that the
man existed in india
300 000 3 lakh years ago
which was the homo sapiens this debunks
the out of africa theory my views
i am aware of the narmada man let's take
a look at what narmada man was and
looked like let me
let's do real time research
okay let's go to
trusty old google
and say narmada
man
so
what does it say about this
person
a possible ancestor of the modern indian
so this is not homo sapiens it's homo
erectus which is
an extinct species
of human
continued okay this in french let's go
back let's see some other uh source
what is this here let's take a look at
what it says here
so
human skeletal remains about 300 to
150 000 years ago middle priestess in
period
is this sapiens what is it
homo erectus this is not homo sapiens
right
so that is the thing it does not
disprove the art of africa theory
it shows we we are quite aware of the
fact that we had other homo species in
asia in eurasia
much
a long time before uh
homo sapiens
arrived
in eurasia
we have the so-called dragon man or
something in in china
we had uh they have found other other uh
fossilized remains
in eastern asia that are more than a
million years old
i think it was homo erectus or something
i'm not sure which which species it was
but yes you have had we have had the
presence of other species of humans
in eurasia long before homo sapiens ever
appeared
in eurasia
so the narmada man was not homo sapiens
he was homo
erectus which is a species that came
before us
so it does not debunk
the out of africa theory
the art of africa theory is the best
theory
we have as of today to explain the
origin
of of uh homo sapiens our species so
according to this theory from the best
data that we have from the overall data
all the data points that we have it
indeed all this data it indicates that
our
our origin was somewhere in africa a
long time ago
about uh
the human chimpanzee divergence is
supposed to have happened about six or
four million years before today before
that we have we were the same species
our ancestors so then so that's where
the origin of the homo
species the various homo species hominin
species
uh occurred in africa and then about 70
75 000 years ago before today there was
an out of africa migration
uh
near yemen djibouti yemen
and that's how the
non-african humans
originated which is again homo sapiens
which is also the you people that you
have in africa
so we have the same species but that's
the art of african migration that uh
that the theory is
which is a theory that you are referring
to so narmada man does not the existence
of narmada man in india does not debunk
the out of africa theory unfortunately
right that's what we just saw
but yeah that's a good question
[Laughter]
if gandhi is a thief well i'm not sure
he's a thief but yeah okay i know i i
understand what your sentiment is then
why did sardar patel support nehru and
gandhi
and why did he
leave the prime minister's seat to
jawaharlal nehru
well that's a very good question
why did mr patel do that he could have
been the prime minister of india
i mean the congress people voted for him
he got 14 votes and mr nero got zero
votes or one vote whatever
it was overwhelmingly in support in
favor of
mr patel
to be the first prime minister of india
then mr gandhi asked patel to step down
and allow mr nehru to become the prime
minister and mr patel agreed
so mr nero was
selected by mr gandhi to be the prime
minister of india it was not a
democratic election by any means
whatsoever
so he became the prime minister of india
undemocratically
and today they teach us democracy they
complain about
not having enough democracy in india
today
so why did mr patel support nehru and
gandhi well i don't know i did that
why did he do that
your allegiance is supposed to be to the
nation and to the people not to some
individual right
so i don't know why mr patel did that
i would also like to remind all of you
about the events of 1946
the great uh
indian navy revolt
which threatened to wipe out britain's
existence in india
if that revolt had gone on for a
week or two more
it would have spread to the indian army
and then within 24 to 48 hours there
will be no europeans left in india
and what happened was that this uh
revolt of the indian navy was quelled by
mr patel
and he actually promised them
the the
the guys who were reading leading the
revolt he promised them that if you lay
down your arms and come back to the fold
then there will be no action taken
against you
and because there was no political
support they laid down their arms
and they were court-martialed and jailed
so this promise was a false promise so
that's mr patel so we have to understand
that all of these
leaders
there are multiple sides to their
personality into the history
i'm not saying he's good or bad or
whatever i'm not passing any judgment
i'm simply pointing to the facts
to the historical facts
so mr patel agreed to step down agreed
to step aside in favor of mr nehru
and we know the consequences of that
decision
it hurt india immensely
so why did mr patel do that why did mr
patel do something that hurt india and
such in such a such a terrible manner
and why did he not support the
the uh
indian naval
revolt
because if he had supported the indian
navy revolt there would have been no
partition of india
right
so yeah it's a history is interesting
very interesting so i don't know why i
did that
only he can answer
okay
why see when when you ask me i mean this
i can see some other questions here
i don't know why he did that i i can't
read people's minds
and i have not studied mr ambedkar in
any detail so i don't know
so there are certain people whom i have
not studied
i have certain interests
and i studied and i study
historical figures and personalities
that align with my interests
i have certain criteria for people whom
i consider to be great
i don't consider a historical figure to
be great
because everybody else calls him great
i have criteria of my own
and if somebody meets those criteria
then i will study that person in detail
other people i simply am not interested
in and that's why i have not studied
many many historical personalities many
important historical personalities
i have not studied them in detail
and one of them is mr ambedkar i'm sure
he was a very significant uh person
he is given the credit credit of framing
india's constitution
okay great all right but
i have not studied his life and his
history and his works etc
in any detail whatsoever and therefore i
am
not aware of why he did this if he
actually did do it so
don't know sorry
who deserves to be called father of
india shashwat asks this
well india was not born in 1947 so
nobody from that time period deserves to
be called the father or the mother or
whatever of india
india is named bharat so it's named
after king bharat so maybe he is one of
the
people
who can be called the founder or the
father of india i can think of some
great historical personalities like lord
ram lord krishna
etc who could come close to
actually deserving such a title
but these little really put in
personalities like bhantas gandhi etc
don't deserve to be called the father of
india
you see
that is my personal opinion i know lots
of people will hate me for saying this
so be it
so i i don't have any any person in mind
who i would say deserves
to be called the one person who is the
father of india india is
a very very old civilization more than
10 000 years old at the minimum so we
don't even know who the real founders
are you know
we don't know
most likely the foundation of our
ethnicity our civilization happened some
sixty seventy thousand years ago
or maybe fifty 60 000 years ago after
the out of africa migration we are the
oldest population group in the world
because we have the
highest genetic diversity in our
population outside of africa
which tells us that we are the oldest
population and ethnic group in the world
so
you know when it comes to indian culture
indian civilization there have been many
people attributed many of those names
are lost in time so i don't think any
person
could be called the father of india if
if one person
has to be given this title it could be
king bharat it could be
king rama
lord krishna perhaps
these people
their work actually has that
has had that impact so you essentially
asking me
who is the greatest indian right
that's what you're actually asking who
can be considered to be the greatest
indian
so what is the criterion
for greatness
that's the that's what i would ask you
again
do you have a set of criteria
for a person to be considered great
i mean is somebody to be considered
great because all the historians call
him or her great
if the romula toppers and irfan habes
called somebody great does it mean does
that mean that that person is great
or is do we need to have a set of
criteria i would say that a person
should be called great
if they have impacted
lots of people in a positive way
the larger your impact the greater you
are
the more lives you touch and transform
the greater you are
and that transformation has to be
positive not negative mouth
killed 100 million chinese so he
impacted at least 100 million chinese
lives but the impact was horrible so i
don't call him great
joseph stalin called killed 30 40
million or more russians so he had a
huge impact but there was a very
negative impact
lord krishna impact impacted an entire
civilization he touched the lives of
millions of people
right he
he changed the destiny of the
subcontinent of indian civilization he
ensured the defeat of the adami adharmic
korvas
and he ensured that the incompetent
panders were sent into exile to the
himalayas now again i'll get hatred for
saying this
did somebody like yudhisthira deserve to
be the king of india a person who could
not control his gambling impulses who
gambled away his wife and his brothers
did a person like that deserve to be the
king of india no
he was incompetent he could not control
his base impulses
did somebody like arjun deserve to be
the king of india he was a great warrior
very brave
but he faltered on the battlefield
he was not willing to fight what's the
point of being a great warrior if you
can't do the right thing the person like
that doesn't deserve to be the king of
india so lord krishna
transformed the entire dynamics of india
he got rid of all these incompetent and
army people
and he did the right thing for the
country
so that is a huge impact he impacted the
entire
civilization and he still revered today
so that is a big positive impact
these are criteria you know
so
so you know that's the kind of criteria
you need to have
to consider somebody great don't
start considering people great and lions
and whatever because everybody else says
that
and then when i say something contrary
to that
i get this backlash so please please use
your intelligence you are all
intelligent
use your intelligent intelligence
have your own criteria
for judging somebody to be great or not
great please do that use your
intelligence don't be sheep
don't use the results of other people's
thinkings
don't form your opinions don't base your
opinions on other people people's
opinions
use your own intelligence please do that
right
okay let's take some more questions
why didn't lord krishna crown himself
the king of bharath because he was not
interested in power okay let me ask let
me ask this question
everybody um
so one of the names of lord krishna is
parthasarthi
the sarthi of the part
means the archer that is arjun so he was
the sarthi the charioteer
of the great warrior arjun right
so it is
people mostly see lord krishna as
somebody who served the pandavas right
so was he serving the pandavas
this in all the political machinations
that lord krishna accomplished
did he do it in the service of the
pandavas
many people tell me that he backstabbed
the pandavas by sending them into exile
and getting rid of them because he had
his own ulterior motives and all the
question is this where is the question
is very simple
whom did lord krishna serve
did he serve the quran we know he did
not but did he serve the pandavas did he
did he participate in the mahabharata
war on behalf of the pandavas
or did he have some other motives the
answer is very simple he served
the civilization he served bharat
he served dharma he got rid of the army
kauravas and then after the war was
finished
he sent the incompetent pandavas into
exile
and then he crowned somebody else as the
king of bharath because he was not
interested in power he was interested in
getting rid of all these people who
would have taken india to its doom
and then he whom did he crown as king i
don't remember some young young guy
i think a descendant of the pandavas i
think so one of the people of that
lineage but somebody knew and somebody
fresh somebody who could be guided in
the right direction so he was not
interested in power he was interested in
serving
the people the culture the civilization
of india and they were interested in
serving dharma he was a servant of
dharma and the people and the
civilization that is why he did not
crown himself king of bharath he was not
doing him all this for personal glory
and personal ambition
that's the reason why that's why he is
considered to be so great that's why
indians today worship him as an
incarnation of lord vishnu the same as
lord rama please understand this
these are lessons in leadership true
leadership
what are my views about
chatrapati shivaji maharaj i think he's
one of the greatest kings of india in
the past 1000 years i have said this
before
uh yeah so in one sentence that's my
view about him one of the greatest
servants of india one of the greatest
leaders of india in the past 1000 years
it's tragic that he died so young
he died in his 50s i think if he had
lived another 10-20 years he could have
transformed india even further and made
india a better place
so it's tragic that he died so young he
was a really really great king
okay let's take some more question
how are brahmans responsible for
conversion of hindus
i have no idea
how brahmins are responsible for any
conversion of anybody
there is this great i mean i i'm not
sure sukhdev if you you have this
but overall we have this this atmosphere
today in india
which is uh driven by the education
system by the leftist by the marxists
of
of anti-brahm brahman sentiment
they now term hinduism as brahmanism
which means that the the
deeper thing is that hinduism is an evil
regressive backward religion
and because they call it brahmanism they
are trying to now
put all the blame on the brahmins so
they are trying to further divide
society and i don't know where all these
stories come from brahman's responsible
for this or that or whatever
so it's it's just
unfortunate it it makes me sad to see
this
you know
so i i don't know in how brahmins are
responsible for any sort of conversion
in any way whatsoever i just don't know
how it is so
that is not consistent with the facts
was nalanda university the best
university of its time i think it was
one of the great universities i think
there were many great universities at
the at the time in ancient india
so i would not say it was the best
university but it was the one that is
the most in the spotlight for what
bhakti or
did there
in one day he beheaded more than 5 000
professors teachers students more than
five thousand i'm sure in one day and
then he burned the library which burned
for several months
so
yeah it was one of the one of the
greatest universities for sure in india
but we had many other great universities
sharda pete in
northern india present-day pakistan
occupied kashmir
fakshila in western india present-day
present-day what punjab pakistani punjab
i think or pakistani one of these two
regions
sheila
vikram sheila in in
where was it was it in bengal
present-day bangladesh
[Music]
i can't remember all of them right now
but we had lots and lots of great
universities on par with nalanda if not
even greater
or the oldest that we know of is
thakshila which is at least two and a
half thousand years old at least it's
probably much much older than that
maybe it's a couple of thousand years
older than that possibly we know that
vishnu gupta chanakya was a professor of
politics and political science in
takshashila university
and that is about
two and a half thousand years before
today so that was already a major
established university at that time two
and a half thousand years before today
so
it's it's clear that it's it would have
been much older than that
so yeah
right let's take some more questions
very interesting questions i'm getting
keep it coming guys and girls keep it
coming love it
okay kunal asks why doesn't india care
about northeast india development and
its culture and heritage
see i'll tell you what yeah it is true
that the northeast of india which is
actually the far east of india it is
totally marginalized and neglected
almost nobody is aware of it
if you ask somebody about money but
they'll say what manipal
right no one knows about this because we
are not this in the education system i
don't know what is being taught in the
education system today but when i was a
kid there was nothing at all
about the northeast of india no
reference to the northeast of india the
only thing was some some
passage in the horrific civics
syllabus
in which you had to memorize all the
capitals of all the states in which you
had to so that's when you came to know
about itanagar and imphal and izal and
all that
but apart from that there was no mention
of in the history the culture etc of
northeastern india
and it is also true that after
independence after the dominion status
of 1947
the
government of india
consciously gave northeast of in
northeast india step motherly treatment
there was absolutely no development in
this region
the uh
mr nehru allowed the rampant
christianization
of the so-called tribal peoples of
northeast india
all the nagas have lost their culture
today
they they believe that their ancestors
were
barbarians
they were uncivilized etc come on man
so it's it's tragic what's happened
the so-called naga people there are
there are
group of different ethnicities different
tribes essentially
they had their own beautiful culture
and the british portrait them as as
as naked people as barbarians as
primitive and that is the first step
towards converting people to
christianity and today the people of
nagaland
and other parts of northeast india have
lost their culture completely they are
completely
rootless
so there was no development there no
infrastructure development no industries
nothing
and that's why so many insurgencies came
up
in
this region
and uh
there were no hospitals developed there
there was no health care nothing
so this is these are the policies of the
nih regime and subsequent congress party
regimes
so that is one of the reasons why
uh it's not that the people of india
don't care about the northeast it's that
the people of india aren't aware about
the northeast if you don't teach
children about the northeast of india
how will they know about it
and then when they see somebody who
comes from assam or nagaland or manipur
they'll think it's from a different
country because the ethnic the ethnic
features look different
that is the is the tragedy of the
northeast
they are as much indian as anybody else
but people just don't know about it
today i think in the 21st century there
is more awareness
but if
the nerubian regime and its successors
were still in power it would be the same
story there
terrorism insurgency separatism and no
development thankfully things are
changing now i hope
there are still major problems in the
northeast
but at least it is going in the right
direction so i would not say that the
people of india don't care about the
northeast and its culture and heritage
it is the government of india
which has always consistently given the
northeast of india step motherly
treatment
right
we tend to blame the people of india for
everything that's wrong with india or
there there is no traffic sense in india
there is garbage everywhere tell me
something
is there any traffic law being
implemented are there any any any uh
traffic police to enforce any laws
and when it comes to the garbage
in india
let's say you put all the garbage in the
trash first of all the government
doesn't provide trash bins
in in the streets and all that so people
are forced to dump the garbage wherever
they can
right they have no control over what
happens outside they can only control
what happens inside their house so
people keep their houses clean but the
outside is all in the hands of the local
municipal councils and whatnot and we
know how they are deeply corrupt many of
them i'm not saying all of them
i'm not saying all are corrupt
but we know that many are corrupt
and many don't care about the people so
that's why you have all these all these
problems garbage now they sometimes will
tell you to segregate garbage into wet
and non-wet or what dry etc and they'll
say that we'll recycle it
do they actually recycle anything they
dump everything into the ocean in the
rivers
so that's the thing right
we tend to blame the people of india for
everything that's gone wrong with india
the truth is it's the colonial
government of india the present day
colonial governance system and
institutions of india that are
responsible for everything that's wrong
in this country
and that is what what the attitudes that
prevail with respect to the northeast
the ignorance about the northeast it's
because
of these government policies education
policies and all that
so i think that once people become aware
of the northeast they do care about the
northeast
but people simply aren't aware the
majority of people today
so that is a great
tragedy of the northeast
deepan says was chanakya a socialist
as claimed by many people as the gap
between
the rich and the poor was less during
the more and more in samraj
you see if you look at socialist this is
a very good question by the way deepan
so if you look at socialist societies
you have this huge gap actually
you have a huge gap look at the ussr
the usr was technically a socialist
nation
the union of
soviet socialist republics
the overall population of the ussr was
in poverty
but the members of the communist party
the politburo they lived in ultra luxury
that was a shocking gap between rich and
poor
look at china
today china is no longer a socialist
country it's a capitalist society
it's an imperial dictatorship with
capital with capitalism but before the
reforms of then shopping
you had the same situation in
socialist china
people living in poverty and the
communist party
bosses living in ultra luxury same thing
you would see
in
fidel castro's cuba
and so on and so forth in the various
soviet block
satellite states of eastern europe the
same situation socialism
inevitably creates a shocking gap
between the rich and the poor it's just
that the poor are so many in number that
it looks like everyone is the same
that's what socialism does
during the mauryan sam raj
everybody was prosperous
just look at the statistics the data of
which angus medicine has
published
india accounted for over a third of the
world's gdp
until 080 and after that before zero a.d
it would have been even more india would
have accounted for more than half the
world gdp that's how prosperous india
was
and the prosperity was not concentrated
among the elites there were no elites
right
the entire population was prosperous the
standards of living were very high that
is not socialism
that is the indian
economic system the dharmic economic
system which did not depend on
the plunder
and the ravaging
of the environment and its resources
it was sustainable development and
growth
so there is no socialism in there you
can read vishnu gupta chanakya's
economic policies in detail in the
arthashastra there was no socialism
there
it's a totally different paradigm that
was in place at the time so that is my
answer sir it's a very interesting
question very good perspective to bring
into this
matter
okay sean says do you think it is
impossible for india to get the u.n
permanent seat because of china i think
it's impossible
the chinese will never allow india to
become uh
a part of the uh
security council
a permanent member of the security
council because it will put india on the
same status on the same level as china
so india was supposed to be the original
member the one of the founding members
of the un security council one of the
five permanent members with veto powers
and all that this was offered to india
repeatedly repeatedly
it was offered in 1950 in 53
and in 55.
first it was offered by the americans to
mr nehru mr nero said no
not at the coast of china please bring
china in first then we'll talk about
india
in 1953 again the americans offered
india they offered mr nehru
a seat
on the permanent seat on the u.n
security council it is written in shashi
thorough's book
sashitharu is a great uh
devotee of mr nehru isn't he mr
shashitaru the great eminent mr shashita
he has written it in his published book
the invention of india or whatever the
hell the name the name of the book is
so 1953 mr nairo was again offered this
he again rejected it in 1955 the us and
ussr got together and again offered the
same thing to india and mr nehru again
rejected it he said not at the cost of
china
put china first
and after that the chinese became
one of the five founding members
permanent members not founding members
but permanent members of the u.n
security council and india was never
considered again
and they can they are now able to use
that power they have
to hurt india in many many many ways
thanks to sri jawal nehru and mr nehru
in parliament in 1955 gave a categorical
statement
that india has never been offered a
permanent state of any kind
in the u.n security council mr nehru
lied in parliament he lied to the people
of india
as prime minister
shocking isn't it
right
okay let's take some more questions
let's take some more questions lots of
questions something interesting that i
have not answered before
why is there a sudden change in the
scripts of the indus valley civilization
and vedic period
at the time of the so-called irene
invasion migration tourism which which
which script has changed
so i am not aware of any sudden or
gradual change in the scripts
of the uh saraswati civilization
i'm not aware of anything we know that
during this phase the saraswati hindu
phase of indian civilization
you have all these uh
tablets etc stereotype tablets clay
tablets on which you have these
symbols that look like a script
and that is still undeciphered so this
saraswati hindu script is not deciphered
yes we know that it's it's there
now where where is the sudden change in
script which new script came in
eventually you had the uh brahmi and
karoshi scripts that came into
uh that that became prevalent but there
was no sudden change
it was a gradual change
and it seems that the brahmi script may
actually be somehow related to the uh
script of the saraswati sindhu phase of
indian civilization and again you don't
you don't find any of these scripts
either the brahmi script or the karoshi
script or the saraswati hindu script
anywhere outside india
so if it was the consequence of a
migration invasion tourism into india
then you would find evidence of these
scripts
outside of india as well
in central asia eastern europe wherever
these
alleged aryans are supposed to have come
from
so that is not the case
right
so like i have been saying so often so
many times i've said this there is not a
single data point
that can
point to an actual rn invasion or
migration or tourism or picnic into
india
i mean they say today based on genetics
that the yamnaya people
are the aryan invaders or migrants into
india right the yamnaya who wiped out
the population of europe the male
population of europe
now the question is if the yamnaya are
the aryan invaders or migrants into
india why didn't they wipe out indian
males
like the way they wiped out the european
why didn't they do that
and in europe you find this sudden
change in the archaeological record a
sudden change in the culture a sudden
change in the burial practices you find
these mass graves of people who have
been murdered brutally and thrown into
the pits
so that is a clear evidence of a
massive invasion
a sudden abrupt change
in everything in europe you don't see
anything like that in india you don't
see any evidence of yamnaya style graves
in india
right show me a single yamnaya burial in
india
anywhere in india in afghanistan in
pakistan in present-day india
anywhere there is not a single such
burial in india so these are all lies
it simply lies that's all i can say
about this
okay
says
was mohandas gandhi a true believer in
the gita if yes why did he always stop
indians to do the real karma which is to
fight the brits for freedom
so here's
a very little known fact about mohandas
gandhi
mohandas gandhi was not a hindu
he was brought up in a sect called the
pranami sect his mother putli putli ben
or putli or whatever her name was
was a member of an obscure minority sect
called the pranami sect
so
if you
research the pranami sect online you
will find what their practices and
beliefs were
in this
sect they held the
torah the bible the old and new
testament
and the bhagavad-gita as sacred texts
and all of these texts were were treated
as sacred texts and they were studied
by the members of the pranami sect
so understand this the bhagavad-gita is
a dharmic text
the torah the bible the new and old
testament in the quran are non-dharmic
texts
essentially you could say these are
dharmic texts and these pranami people
they hold these non-dharmic texts
to be sacred
which tells you that this is not a
dharmic sect
right
and mr gandhi
has written about this that he grew up
uh
reading the bible the quran etc
and he considered these books to be
sacred books for him
so one could not one cannot make the
claim that he was a true believer in the
gita or that he was a real hindu
if you considered a non-dharmic text to
be a sacred text that automatically
makes you not a hindu
it's very simple
so mr gandhi was not a hindu please
understand this
he
i mean historians and the media etc they
portray him as a great dharma guru or
whatever
he was the exact opposite
of that
and that kind of explains
much of his
political
actions
right
uh could you please tell us the
significance of the kerala school of
mathematics in the field of
astronomy and mathematics calculus
so the kerala school of mathematics was
a wonderful
group of mathematicians it was a very
good mathematical tradition that spanned
several centuries it was wiped out by
tipu sultan
the tyrant the butcher of mysore
so
they had
amazing mathematicians like neela kanta
i think one of them and the jesh
one of them one of the names was
and they essentially
discovered calculus
at least two centuries before
newton is supposed to have discovered
calculus
so they discovered a
calculus infinite series
and much more
and it was jesuit priests who came to
india who stole this knowledge
transmitted it to the west
and that's how it was independently
discovered
by
newton and leibniz
in the same year
imagine something as momentous
a discovery as calculus
being as accidentally discovered by two
europeans
one in europe one in britain
one in england and one in germany
in the same year how is it even possible
is can can that be a coincidence no it's
not a coincidence it means both of these
guys got their hands on a translation
and they both claim to have discovered
it independently
and then there was a big dispute between
the two of them as to who was the first
neither was the first
it was indians who discovered calculus
the kerala school of mathematics
today these facts are now coming to
light but but today western historians
are trying to say that it was accidental
in
newton and leibniz discovered calculus
independently there was no transmission
it was something that was discovered
independently which is a lie it was all
stolen by jesuit priests
and transmitted to europe after being
translated
okay let's
see some more
questions
i'll take one or two more questions
because we are reaching our time limit
okay let's see
richard says why is there such a death
of public works such as aqueducts etc
in indian history after the harappan
phase see india is a river valley
civilization
we have river valley all of our
settlements towns cities etc they are
built around rivers in river valleys
this sindhu uh indus valley the
saraswati valley the seven great rivers
in the punjab regions of the region
those river valleys the narmada valley
the tapti valley the ganga valley the
godavari valley and and so many more
india is a river valley civilization and
when you have such incredible
gifts of nature so many great rivers
then you don't need to build aqueducts
an aqueduct is a work of engineering
that transports water over long
distances that's what the roman
engineers built
because the places they ruled like judea
etc central europe and so on
there was
a dearth of water there
in india we did not have that
we had rivers everywhere
so many rivers so many natural resources
and that's why we did not need to build
aqueducts but we did build great
highways
the great uh the so called great trunk
road grand trunk road whatever which is
alleged to have been built by sher shah
suri that road was in existence during
the mauryan times
right it was a very well maintained road
a very well maintained highway it
connected partly putra in the east of
india to takshashila and further
in the west of india
which is present at bihar and east of
bihar in present-day
pakistan
and west
and this was a very well maintained road
you had
rest houses
you had ins you had hospitals
you had hospitals for animals all of
this all maintained by the state all
free of charge you did not have to pay
money to use the hospital or the rest
house or the inn or whatever
that's the kind of
public works
we had in india
before the past one thousand years
interesting
okay other says wikipedia says mahatma
gandhi's mother was a prize pious
pranami hindu
pranami hindu is an oxymoron it doesn't
go together
pranami's are not hindus if you worship
non-dharmic texts
if you consider non-dharmic texts
as sacred texts
you are not a hindu
simple
so i don't care what wikipedia says
if you worship non-dharmic text you
cannot be considered to be hindu it's as
simple as that
all religions are not the same there are
only three religions
the three abrahamic religions hinduism
is not a religion it's a cult it's a
culture it's a civilization
we don't have one book one god and one
prophet
right
and we don't consider other religions to
be inferior and we don't believe that
you will go to hell if you don't worship
my book my prophet and my god
which is what these other three
religions do so if you consider their
texts to be sacred you are no longer a
dharmic person it's as simple as that
so she may be a pious pranami but she
was not a hindu
okay
any other questions let me see
okay let me see one more if i can find
something interesting
where can i read the vedas in puranas i
am not sure i think uh
you may find some copies online if you
look
uh it depends on which language you want
to read it in there are some
translations of the vedas and vedas in
english but i am not sure how reliable
or accurate those translations will be
because there are many many sanskrit
words that cannot be translated properly
into english
for instance yagna
is translated as sacrifice
yagna is not a sacrifice a sacrifice is
a ritual murder
yagna is not a sacrifice but that's how
they translate
our vedic texts so i don't know if they
can actually be relied upon to actually
gain in real knowledge
i think you will find translations
online you may be able to buy
translations on various online
portals like flipkart amazon whatever
i'm not sure about the puranas where you
can find them but if you look online you
may be able to find most of these things
some of it may be available only in
sanskrit for which you may need to learn
sanskrit which is not a difficult thing
to do
so that's what i can say in brief
what would have happened if the british
had not come to india what would modern
day india look like if the british had
not come to india we would all be
speaking marathi or sanskrit
because the british destroyed the
maratha empire the marathas had already
annihilated the mughal empire
the mughal uh
emperor emperor still existed
but he was essentially the mayor of
delhi that's all he was
right the marathas
they they
controlled the entirety of india
most of india from much of southern
india to northern and western india
eastern india much of it
and all the way up to southern
afghanistan
so that was the maratha empire that's
what the british destroyed
if they had not come to india we would
be a dharmic state
the hindu russia that everybody demands
and our national language would either
have been marathi or sanskrit
which would be
a million times better than what it is
today
so that's what would have happened if
the british had not come to india
all right ladies gentlemen
boys and girls thank you so much for all
the questions
it was wonderful chatting to you all
and i will see you very soon next week
in next week's episode
thank you very much thank you very much
all of you
i will see you